Guide to the Lawrence Pratt Collection Concerning Arizona v. California and the Colorado River
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lawrence Pratt collection concerning Arizona v. California and the Colorado River
1948-1960
WA MSS S-2613
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2
(2 boxes)
The collection consists of printed exhibits, engineering reports, witness testimony, and speeches relating to the court case, Arizona v. California, which concerned water rights to the Colorado River and its tributaries and which also involved a boundary dispute between the Fort Mojave Indian Reservation and the Colorado River Indian Reservation. These materials were seemingly collected by Lawrence Pratt in his position as Senior Hydraulic Engineer at the Colorado River Board of California, and shed particular light on California's side of the court case.
Pratt, Lawrence
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Marc Selvaggio, Bookseller on the Arthur Corbitt Hoskins Memorial Fund, 2008.
Custodial History
From the collection of an unidentified, retired engineer in San Diego.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Lawrence Pratt
Lawrence Pratt was a civil engineer based in Los Angeles, and also served as Senior Hydraulic Engineer with the Colorado River Board of California from 1949 to at least 1958 and possibly later. In 1958, he testified as an expert witness for the California defendants in the Fort Mojave Indian Reservation and Colorado River Indian Reservation boundary dispute.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of printed exhibits, engineering reports, witness testimony, and speeches relating to the court case, Arizona v. California, which concerned water rights to the Colorado River and its tributaries and which also involved a boundary dispute between the Fort Mojave Indian Reservation and the Colorado River Indian Reservation. These materials were seemingly collected by Lawrence Pratt in his position as Senior Hydraulic Engineer at the Colorado River Board of California, and shed particular light on California's side of the court case.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. California Exhibits, 1956-1958. II. Other Records, 1948-1960.
Indians of North America -- Water rights; Water rights -- Arizona; Water rights -- California; Water rights -- Southwest, New; Water rights -- Southwestern States; Water-supply -- Arizona; Water-supply -- California; Water-supply -- Southwest, New; Water-supply -- Southwestern States; Arizona -- Trials, litigation, etc.; California -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico) -- Water rights; Colorado River Indian Reservation (Ariz. and Calif.); Fort Mojave Indian Reservation; Pratt, Lawrence; Colorado River Board of California
- California Exhibits, 1956-1958; 1.5
  Scope and Contents
  Printed exhibits, including folding maps, charts, tables, and reprints of primary documents which shed light on the historical background of California's long-term use of Colorado River water.
  - Exhibit No. 1-100, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Exhibit No. 101-170, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - Exhibit No.171-270, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
  - Exhibit No. 271-351, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 13-16)
  - Exhibit No. 371-449, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Exhibit No. 371-446, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
  - Exhibit No. 450-550, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 23-26)
  - Exhibit No. 2000-2099, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 27-30)
  - Exhibit No. 2100-2174, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
  - Exhibit No. 2200-2217, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Exhibit No. 2301, 2401, 2402, 2620, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Exhibit No. 2643-2644, 2701-2723, 2901-2904, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Other Records, 1948-1960; 0.5
  - Arizona Exhibits, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "Arizona v. California: Gila River Basin - Physical Data Book", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 38-41)
    Reports prepared by hydraulic engineers from Colorado River Board, covering topics such as topography, drainage, climate, vegetation, water source and quality, history of development, agriculture, industry, business, and irrigation, among others. Included are numerous folded maps.
  - "Engineering Data Urgently Required for Preparation of California Defendants", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    A compilation of reports and memos, presumably for internal circulation for Colorado River Board, regarding water resources and use in Arizona, with estimates regarding the proposed Central Arizona Project and Arizona's use of Colorado River water.
  - Testimony of Lawrence Pratt on Fort Mojave Indian Reservation and Colorado Indian Reservation Boundary Controversies, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Pratt's copy of his own testimony, including three folding maps and eight original snapshots.
  - Use of Water by California Agencies and Reasonableness of Use, circa 1956 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Coker, C. E., "Arizona versus California" (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Raver, Paul J., Hydro - The Energy Base of the Northwest: An Address Before the Institute for Social Action, First Methodist Church, Portland, Oregon, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Steiner, Wesley E., Arizona v. California: Presentation to Hydraulics Group of Los Angeles Section, American Society of Civil Engineers, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 47)